A Guide to the Commonwealth Fund records, Vertical File (Reginald H. Fitz), SG 1, Series 34 FA306
Rockefeller Archive Center
Commonwealth Fund records, Vertical File (Reginald H. Fitz), SG 1, Series 34
1953-1979
Rockefeller Archive Center
Commonwealth Fund
FA306
1.52 Cubic Feet 4 document boxes
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Biographical/Historical note
The Commonwealth Fund was established in 1918 with an endowment of $10 million from Mrs. Stephen V. Harkness for "benevolent, religious, educational and like purposes." The early grants supported a variety of programs while generally promoting welfare, especially child welfare. Several grants were made in the field of medical research, but the Board of Directors decided in 1920 that this field was already sufficiently supported by other philanthropic organizations.
Despite this decision, by the mid-1920s the chief interest of the Fund had become public health, including mental hygiene, community health, rural hospitals, medical research, and medical education. Other grant areas included war relief, educational and legal research, child welfare, and international medical fellowships.
File Plan note
Former Classification: IX; IV 4B 4
Other Finding Aids
Other available finding aids describing the Commonwealth Fund records include:
FA247 Commonwealth Fund Harkness House drawings
FA276 Commonwealth Fund records, Annual Reports, SG 1, Series 4
FA277 Commonwealth Fund records, Archives/Library, SG 1, Series 5
FA278 Commonwealth Fund records, Austrian Program, SG 1, Series 6
FA279 Commonwealth Fund records, Board of Directors, SG 1, Series 7
FA280 Commonwealth Fund records, Capital Grants, SG 1, Series 8
FA281 Commonwealth Fund records, Child Health Demonstrations, SG 1, Series 9
FA282 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Community Clinics, SG 1, Series 10
FA283 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Health Studies, SG 1, Series 11
FA284 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Public Health, SG 1, Series 12
FA285 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Publications, SG 1, Series 13
FA286 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Rural Hospitals, SG 1, Series 14
FA287 Commonwealth Fund records, Educational Research, SG 1, Series 15
FA288 Commonwealth Fund records, English Mental Hygiene Program, SG 1, Series 16
FA289 Commonwealth Fund records, Finance Committee, SG 1, Series 17
FA290 Commonwealth Fund records, Grants, SG 1, Series 18
FA291 Commonwealth Fund records, Harkness Family, SG 1, Series 19
FA292 Commonwealth Fund records, Harkness Fellowships, SG 1, Series 20
FA428 Commonwealth Fund records, Harkness Fellowships, Fellows Reports, SG 1, Series 20A
FA293 Commonwealth Fund records, Institute for Child Guidance, SG 1, Series 21
FA294 Commonwealth Fund records, Interface Program, SG 1, Series 22
FA295 Commonwealth Fund records, Legal Research Program, SG 1, Series 23
FA296 Commonwealth Fund records, Living at Home Program, SG 1, Series 24
FA297 Commonwealth Fund records, Mental Hygiene Program, SG 1, Series 25
FA298 Commonwealth Fund records, Miscellaneous - unprocessed
FA299 Commonwealth Fund records, Personnel - unprocessed
FA300 Commonwealth Fund records, Pilgrim Trust, SG 1, Series 28
FA301 Commonwealth Fund records, Program for the Prevention of Delinquency, SG 1, Series 29
FA302 Commonwealth Fund records, Reference Files, SG 1, Series 30
FA303 Commonwealth Fund records, Reports of the General Director, SG 1, Series 31
FA304 Commonwealth Fund records, Treasurer, SG 1, Series 32
FA305 Commonwealth Fund records, Turndown Lists, SG 1, Series 33 - unprocessed
FA306 Commonwealth Fund records, Vertical File (R. Fitz), SG 1, Series 34 - unprocessed
FA307 Commonwealth Fund records, Visual Materials, SG 1, Series 35
FA389 Commonwealth Fund records, Administration - Historical Files, SG 1, Series 1
FA390 Commonwealth Fund records, Administration - Officers Files, SG 1, Series 2
FA429 Commonwealth Fund records, President, Margaret E. Mahoney, SG 2, Series 1
FA430 Commonwealth Fund records, Book Program, SG 2, Series 2
Arrangement
Records remain arranged as received.
Scope and Contents
This series is a vertical file created by Reginald H. Fitz consisting of articles, reports, studies, reprints and other associated subject matter.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Commonwealth Fund records were donated to RAC in 1985. Record transfers began in 1986, and accruals continue. This series was accessioned as 1986:069.
Medical research; Medical education; Medicine -- Scholarships, fellowships, etc.; Medicine, Rural; Mental health; New York (State); New York (N.Y.); Public welfare; Public health; War relief; United States; Hygiene; Child welfare; Child mental health; Child psychology
- Vertical File (Reginald H. Fitz), 1953-1979; 34
  - Essay on A Design for a Medical School Curriculum (Box 1)
  - Article - A Medical Classic: The Care of the Patient, Francis W. Peabody (Box 1)
  - New Medical Education in Old Southwest, Fitz and Stone (Box 1)
  - Article - Role of the Two-Year School in Easing the Shortage of Physicians (Box 1)
  - Osteopathy and Medicine (Box 1)
  - National Health Insurance: What Kind and How Much - Second of Two Parts, Robert D. Eilers (Box 1)
  - Article - Phone Lectures Link Community Hospitals to University Centers (Box 1)
  - Article - The Problem of Pot (Southwestern Medicine) (Box 1)
  - Article - What Direction for National Health Insurance (Box 1)
  - Article - Physicians in Residence (Box 1)
  - Article - Detriments of Medical Care - A Plan for the Future (Box 1)
  - Home Hemodialysis: Six Years Experience - Blagg, Hickman, Eschbach, Scribner (Box 1)
  - Case Records of the Massachusetts General Hospital (New England Journal) (Box 1)
  - Health Reform of a Frugal Budget (Box 1)
  - Conceptual Developments in Psychosomatic Medicine: 1939-1969, Chase Patterson Kimball (Box 1)
  - Some Bottlenecks Through Family Medicine, LeRoy P. Levitt (Box 1)
  - Bacterial Endocarditis (Grand Rounds) (Box 1)
  - Health Policy Directions for the 1970s, William L. Kissick (Box 1)
  - Indian Health (Box 1)
  - Electro-Shock Therapy (Box 1)
  - Reprints - Chickenpox (Varicella) (Box 1)
  - Reprints - Exchangeable Potassium Content of the Body in Congestive Failure (Box 1)
  - Reprints - Postoperative Hypotension Associated with Hypokalemia (Box 1)
  - Colorado Tick Fever - Fitz and Meiklejohn (Box 1)
  - Colorado Tick Fever (Box 1)
  - Article - The Epidemiology of Lung Cancer (Box 2)
  - Applying Risk Factor Analysis to Screening - AIAA Paper No. 71-537 (Box 2)
  - Article - National Health Insurance: What Kind and How Much, Robert D. Eilers (Box 2)
  - Are We Building Too Many Medical Schools, Kenneth B. Castleton (Box 2)
  - The Challenge of Medicine in the 1970s, Chase Patterson Kimball (Box 2)
  - Shattuck Lecture - The Anatomy of our Melancholy, George Himler (Box 2)
  - Regional Medical Programs in Search of a Mission, Anthony L. Komaroff (Box 2)
  - Cancer Research: The Great Debate, Sir Alexander Haddow (Box 2)
  - President's Health Message - 1971 (Box 2)
  - A Bookshelf on Community Planning for Health, Marvin D. Strauss, MPH, FAPHA and Ido de Groot, MPH (Box 2)
  - Book Reviews - The Spanish-speaking, JAHA (Box 2)
  - The Cure of Plague - Two Viewpoints, William P. Reed, Eppie D. Rael, Ulton G. Hodgin, Jr. (Box 2)
  - Rural Health Care Systems, Vernon E. Wilson (Box 2)
  - For Medical Electronic Gear, Hospitals are not very healthy places (Box 2)
  - Liberal Thought, Radical Theory and Medical Practice, Micheal J. Halberstam (Box 2)
  - The Urgency of Social Action for Health, Lester Breslow, AJPH, Vol. 60, No. 1 (Box 2)
  - Article - Geographic Patern of Hypertension in Colorado (Box 2)
  - Slave Doctors and Free Doctors (Box 2)
  - The Leadership Role in Future Environmental Management, Environmental Services Division, HSSD (Box 2)
  - The Health of Americans - Aspen Institute-American Assembly (Box 2)
  - Health Insurance for the Nation, Stanley W. Olson (Box 2)
  - Hospital Patient Statistics, Jane H. Murnaghan and Kerr L. White (Box 2)
  - The Economics of Health Care Delivery, Anne R. Somers (Box 2)
  - Public Education, A Responsibility of Our Scientific Societies, Jack H. Oppenheimer (Box 2)
  - The NIH and US Medical Schools: The Next 25 Years, Marvin D. Siperstein (Box 2)
  - In Defense of the Establishment, Robert G. Petersdorf (Box 2)
  - Effects of Treatment on Mobidity in Hypertension, VA Study (Box 2)
  - Psychologic and Social Precursors of Coronary Disease, C. David Jenkins (Box 2)
  - Psychologic and Social Precursors of Coronary Disease, Part II, C. David Jenkins (Box 2)
  - A Health Care System for Massachusetts, Cronkhite, Alpert, Weiner (Box 2)
  - Effects of Treatment on Mobidity in Hypertension, VA Study (Box 2)
  - A Double Blind Control Study of Antihypertensive Agents, VA Study (Box 2)
  - Science and Government Report (Box 2)
  - Swedish Medical Care in Transition, Lars Werko (Box 2)
  - Hospital Economics - If Doctors Owned the Hospitals, Morton C. Creditor (Box 2)
  - Hospital Economics - The Computer as a Consultant, Howard L. Bleich (Box 2)
  - Chicken Pox (Box 2)
  - Community Health (Box 2)
  - Health Manpower Ulilization (Box 2)
  - Heart Disease (Box 2)
  - Varicella Pneumonia (Box 2)
  - Cerebrovascular Disease (Box 2)
  - Basic Biology (Box 2)
  - Carcinoma (Box 2)
  - Alerations in Exchangeable Sodium Content - Congestive Heart Failure, Aikawa and Fitz (Box 3)
  - Masculinizing Carcinoma - A Case Report 1956, Annals of Internal Medicine (Box 3)
  - Mercurialism (Box 3)
  - Reprints of Ward Darley (Box 3)
  - Article - Controlling Costs of Medical Care by Expanding Insurance Coverage (Box 3)
  - Prediction of Success in Medical School (Draft for Publication by Reginald H. Fitz) (Box 3)
  - University of New Mexico - Proposals for the Curriculm, Fitz (Box 3)
  - Varicella Pneumonia in Adults, Fitz and Meiklejohn (Box 3)
  - Evaluation of Health Service Programs (Box 3)
  - Exchangeable Potassium Content - Congestive Failure (Box 3)
  - Distribution of HG203- Labeled Mercaptomerin in Human Tissues (Box 3)
  - Psychiatric Reprints (Box 3)
  - Plague (Box 3)
  - Prediction of Success in Medical School, Conger and Fitz (Box 3)
  - Psittacosis in Colorado, Fitz and Meiklejohn (Box 3)
  - Geriatrics (Box 4)
  - Medical Education (Box 4)